Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太＞
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
＜栄光の日 生まれの
ひびと
弟･日々人は➡
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
日本人初の
ムーンウォーカーとなった＞
＜月面望遠鏡建設を望む➡
Older brother Mutta seeks to become an astronaut, and keep his promise to former teacher Sharon,
恩師･シャロンとの
約束を果たすため➡
兄･六太は
宇宙飛行士を目指す＞
to build a telescope on the moon.
Mutta's made it through the first round, but he keeps running into trouble.
＜選抜試験を
かろ
辛うじて突破するが➡
訓練中もトラブルの連続！
筆記試験では最低点＞
On the written test, he scores the lowest.
And as a result, he's assigned to a wild flight instructor.
＜暴走教官が
飛行訓練の担当になる始末＞
＜だが 困難に揉まれたおかげで➡
However, the older brother Mutta
has yet to realize that he's rapidly learning the lessons he'll need to become an astronaut.
宇宙飛行士の大事な資質を➡
猛スピードで
身に付けていることに➡
兄･六太は
まだ気づいていない＞
なんば
(南波六太)｢９Ｎ塔へ来い｣か…｡
"Come to building 9N"?
Why did you turn down a chance to make it into space quickly?
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)なぜ断ったのですか｡
宇宙への一番の近道を｡
申し訳ないです｡
どうしても月へ…｡
私でさえ➡
I feel bad about it, but I'm determined to reach the moon...
I have yet...
私でさえ まだ月へは
行けてないんですよ｡
I have yet to go to the moon.
Wh-What is this place?
ここは？
ここはバギーやローバー➡
This is where buggies, rovers, and other vehicles are developed for use on the moon's surface.
その他 月面基地局の
開発部署です｡
彼らはここの技術者達｡
They're the engineers here.
(ﾋﾟｰﾀｰ)なんだ～｡
ま～た男なの？
What's this? Another man?
In any case,
とにかく君はここで
何らかの成果を上げてください｡
you must produce results here.
それができれば君にも➡
If you're able to do that, you'll have a shot
月ミｯシｮンのバｯクアｯプクルｰへの
道が開けます｡
at a backup crew spot for a lunar mission.
正直 タイヤもブレーキも
今以上の物を求められても➡
Honestly, after racking our brains on changing the tires and brakes, we've been coming up with nothing.
頭がねじれるばっかりだわ｡
だって ほぼ完璧だもん｡
I mean, they're essentially perfect as they are.
(ﾀﾞﾝ)でも このままじゃ
僕らの…➡
But if we do nothing, we'll take a hit to our pride as NASA engineers.
ナサ
ＮＡＳＡの技術者としての
プライドがさ｡
《落ちないバギーか…》
A buggy that won't fall, huh?
Everything's green, with all the bushes and trees.
芝と木のある風景に飢えてるよ｡
リンダは？
What about you, Linda?
(ﾘﾝﾀﾞ)私は家族との
バーベキューが楽しみ｡
I'm looking forward to a family barbecue.
ヒビトはどうだ？
And you, Hibito?
I'm planning on taking my bike for a ride.
俺はやっぱり…➡
愛用のチャリンコに乗って
どっか行くだろうね｡
好きだな～自転車｡
You love that bike of yours, huh?
まっ 相当ホコリ
被ってるだろうけど｡
Well, it's probably covered in dust.
(管制官)ヒビトの心拍数が
上昇してますが｡
Hibito's heart rate is rising.
本人に伝える必要はない｡
He doesn't need that information.
予定通り打ち上げてやろう｡
Continue with the launch.
大丈夫？ヒビト｡
苦しいのか？
Are you okay, Hibito?
Are you in any pain?
何言ってんの｡
大丈夫 大丈夫｡
What's this about?
I'm doing just fine.
さあ…帰ろう！
Okay, let's go home.
It's just obvious that the more you put in your bag
The heavier it gets
The harder I work, the closer I get to my goal
But I'm just not getting there fast enough
I gaze at the night sky but it doesn't calm me down
Now that you've heard how loud my heart's beating
Let's take a trip outside
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of dreams and reality
I'm currently updating the canvas of my dreams
With a glittering universe and a blue earth
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of facades and honesty
I'm currently conversing with the canvas of my dreams
On this orbit of fate
With a fire in my belly
#71 Rehearsal
(アポ)フガ フガ フガッ…｡
[ｹｲﾀｲ](南波母)ポン酢？何のポン酢!?
Ponzu?
What kind?
No, not ponzu.
違う違う！｢ジャポンズ｣！
Japons...
ああ～ じゃ ぽんずね！へぇ～｡
Oh, ja ponzu?
それ どんなポン酢？
☎だからポン酢じゃないって！
What kind of ponzu is that?
I'm not asking for ponzu!
日本で売ってるビジネス雑誌だよ｡
タイトルが｢ジャポンズ｣！
It's a business magazine, published in Japan.
The title is Japons...
その雑誌の表紙になるの｡
俺と日々人が｡宇宙服で！
Hibito and I are going to be on the cover.
Wearing our spacesuits.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](母)あら～ ホント～！
２人で表紙に！
Oh, really?
You boys on the cover?
ねえ お父さん！雑誌の表紙に
なるんだって 六太と日々人！
Hey, dear...
Mutta and Hibito are going to be on the cover of a magazine.
Wow, I'm so excited...
いやぁ～ ドキドキね それ｡
ねえ 緊張してる？緊張してる？
So, are you nervous?
Nervous?
まあ ちょっとしてるけど
大丈夫でしょ｡あれ ズボンは？
Well, I'm a little nervous, but it's fine.
Eh, where are my pants?
(母)それで いつ発売なの？それ｡
And which issue will it be?
I'm not sure... I'll let you know once I find out.
ガフッ…｡
分かんないけど
聞いたら連絡するよ｡
はいは～い わかった おやすみ！
Okay, I got it!
Good night!
あっ そっち朝なの？あ そっか｡
Oh, is it morning over there?
Right...
は～い おはよ～！
いってらっしゃ～い！
Okay, good morning! Have a nice day!
(南波父)雑誌って 何の雑誌だ？
Which magazine is it?
Oh, um...
ああ ええっとね
ポン酢の雑誌だって｡
A ponzu magazine.
《ポン酢の雑誌…》
A ponzu magazine?
誰が…買うんだ？
Who would buy that?
あ～まったく…こんな頭で
雑誌の表紙は飾れねえよな｡
Man...
I can't be on a magazine cover with hair like this...
《ムフフ…カッコ良すぎる》
I think I look pretty cool.
よ～し！んおっ！
Okay!
っぶね～…ま～だあった｡
One more spot...
日々人～ そろそろ行くぞ～｡
Hibito, we should get going.
ふわぁ…俺もう行けるよ～｡
いつでも｡
I'm ready to go anytime.
Uh...
You're going to a photo studio like that?
お前…撮影なのに
そんなカッコで行くのかよ？
ムッちゃんこそ それは？
And what about you, Mu?
Huh?
変だよ｡
You look weird...
いやいや 今朝からズボンが
見つかんないんだよ！
(アポ)ワンワン！ガフガフ…➡
Oh, I can't find my pants.
Huh?
ガフガフ…ワンワン！ワンワン！
あったわ…｡
There they are.
Oh, yeah.
ああ そうだ｡
日々人 月面バギーなんだけどさ｡
Hibito, a question on the lunar buggy...
やっぱ 月面だと勝手が違うだろ？
Hmm?
I'm guessing it works differently on the moon.
運転しづらい点とか
教えといてくれ｡
Before you leave for Russia, can you tell me if there were any issues?
ロシアに発つ前に｡
まあ 詳しいことなら
実際に運転してたダミアンに➡
Well, if you want details, you should probably ask Damian since he was driving...
聞いた方が確実だけど…｡
とりあえず ブレーキは
ここみたいにはきかねえな｡
But the brakes weren't as responsive.
Since there's less gravity, brakes generate less friction, and it's harder to stop.
重力が小さい分
まさつ
地面との摩擦が弱まって➡
簡単には止まってくれねえし…｡
スリップもしやすい｡
And the buggy slides around a lot...
なるほろ…｡
I see.
《ってことは…》
Which means...
《ピーター達が今やってる
ブレーキの改良とかって➡
Peter and the guys are probably wasting their time trying to improve the brakes.
あんまり意味ねえのかもな…》
《う～ん…》
Morning!
おはよ～｡
あの人
俺のサポートスタッフの小林さん｡
That's Kobayashi, from my support staff.
あ ああ ちゃんと話すの
初めてだな｡
Oh, I don't think I've talked to her before.
どうも 日々人が
お世話になってます｡
Hello! Thank you for always helping Hibito.
I should thank you for coming today.
(小林)こちらこそ｡今日はご協力
ありがとうございます｡
The editors have come from Tokyo for this.
もう編集部の皆さんも
来られてますよ｡
今日のために東京から｡
Oh? They came all the way here?
ゴホッ｡
スッゲ～な このセット！
This set is incredible!
Yes, we're just borrowing it.
借り物ですけどね➡
映画とかで
昔 使ってたらしいです｡
I believe that it's been used in movies.
へえ～ 本物みたいだな…｡
Wow... It looks so real.
Except I've never been on the moon, so I wouldn't know.
《つっても 行ったことないから
知らないけど》
Is this what we're wearing for the photo?
《これ 撮影で着るやつかな》
《ム！何？このネクタイ…
長っげ～！》
What's with the tie?
It's so long...
《誰？こんな首太い人》
Is there someone with a really thick neck?
まっ 今回の表紙のテーマは➡
If you had time to read through the proposal, it discusses the theme of this cover.
お読み頂いた企画書の通り
なんですが➡
日本人ムーンウォーカー第１号
南波日々人さん！そして➡
We have Nanba Hibito, the first Japanese moonwalker.
And his big brother, Mutta, who's following him into space.
その後を追って 月へ向かう
兄の六太さん！➡
同じ舞台で追いつ追われつ
頑張っているライバル兄弟を➡
The idea is to show two rival brothers, competing in the same environment.
テーマにですね
まあ今のお２人の姿を通じて➡
We're trying to use this image to send a message to hard-working folks worldwide.
世の働く人々にメッセージとして
感じとって頂こうと➡
Anyway, that's the concept.
まあそういうコンセプトなんです｡
それはまあ わかるんですけど…｡
I get that part...
なんか おかしくないすか？
この格好…｡
But this doesn't look quite right.
Now, now...
元サラリーマンが宇宙飛行士に➡
The idea is that a former white-collar office worker has become an astronaut and is on his way to space.
なって 今まさに
宇宙を目指しているという➡
It's a visual representation to show
まあ 表現なんですね これ｡
今 その途中にいるんだと！
that you're still on your way to space.
《俺の衣裳だったのか
このネクタイ》
So this tie really was for me...
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)≪日々人さん 入りま～す≫
Hibito's coming in.
あっ お疲れさまで～す！
Ah, thank you!
Wow, what a nice set.
うわぁ～ すごいセットだね｡
イーグルじゃん！
That's Eagle...
(編集者)じゃあ お２人 そちらの
月面に並んで下さい｡➡
Then we'll need you two to stand on the moon's surface,
and we'll start taking pictures.
試し撮りしていきますんで｡
《う～ん…この格好で月にいたら
俺は死ぬわけだけど…》
If I stood on the moon dressed like this, I'd die.
《この人達は
分かってるんだろうか…》
Do these people realize that?
あれ？ムッちゃん 下は？
Huh?
Where's the rest of your spacesuit, Mu?
I wish I were standing next to Serika...
《ど～せなら せりかさんと並んで
撮ってもらいてぇな あ～あ…》
Man...
《元気かな～ せりかさん》
I wonder how she's doing.
変だよ｡
You look weird.
これはな
コンセプトだ コンセプト｡
See, that's the picture's concept...
The concept.
What's wrong, Hibito?
どうした 日々人？
It's nothing...
いや 何もないよ｡
Looks good!
いいね～｡ああ 六太さん！
Oh, Mutta...
１枚どうぞ 記念に｡
ああ どうも｡
You can have one as a souvenir.
Oh, thank you.
《変なの…》
I look weird.
以上で撮影終了で～す！
お疲れ様で～す！
The shoot's over!
Great job, guys!
Let's give a big thank you to the Nanba brothers!
南波兄弟のお２人
ありがとうございました～！
(ピーター)タイヤも ブレーキも➡
In terms of tires and brakes, we've exhausted our options.
もうやりきったでしょ｡
これ以上 改良の余地ある？
Can we improve anything else?
I was talking to Hibito...
日々人に聞いたんだけどさ｡
月面は重力が小さい分➡
And he said that the moon's lower gravity diminishes the brakes' effectiveness.
そもそも ブレーキが
効きにくいって｡
これってつまり すげ～いい
ブレーキやタイヤがあっても➡
Which means that no matter how good the brakes or tires are,
効果には 限界がある
ってことじゃないかな？
they can only do so much.
え!?じゃあ ブレーキやタイヤを
改良したって意味ないってこと？
So there's no point in improving the brakes and tires?
今までやってきた…｡
Our work was for nothing?
Well... I guess.
まあ…そうだね｡
ほうら これだから
早くダミアン達に➡
See?
I told you we should talk to Damian and the other astronauts.
話 訊いとけって言ったでしょ｡
訊かなくていいっつったの
お前だろ ピーター｡
You're the one who said we didn't need to talk to them.
This is bad.
(ハロルド)まずいぞ 上から
なんて言われるか…｡
The brass won't like this.
あ～ じゃあ こういうのどう？
Ah, how does this sound?
ウチらのバギーは 完ペキなんで➡
Our buggy is fine,
あとは 飛行士の
運転技術をみがいて➡
so the focus should be on training astronauts not to drive off cliffs.
穴に落ちないようにしてください
って言うの｡
お～ 我ながら
なんて真っ当な意見でしょう｡
I have to say, that makes perfect sense.
誰が言うの？
Who would say that?
俺以外の誰か｡
Someone who isn't me.
まてよ 諦めるのは
まだ早いぜ みんな｡
Hold on...
It's too early to give up, guys.
おぉ…何かいい考えがあんのか？
Oh? Do you have a good idea?
Sure...
それを みんなで考えよう！
Let's come up with a good idea!
すんげえ 真っ当な意見だぁ～｡
That makes perfect sense...
いいな～ ロシア！
美人いっぱいいるんだろうな～｡
Russia is a nice place.
I bet there are lots of pretty girls...
But it's cold.
でも 寒いよ｡
まあ しばらく帰ってこれね～けど
その間 アポをよろしくね みんな｡
Well, I won't be back for a while,
so can you look after Apo for me?
(オジー)ああ アポのことは
任せとけ！
Yep, sure thing.
あ おみやげ マトリョーシカね｡
Oh, bring me a matryoshka doll.
気をつけていってらっしゃい｡
Take care of yourself.
じゃあな ムッちゃん｡
バギー がんばれよ！
See ya, Mu.
Good luck with the buggy.
おう！小学生でも
運転できるようにしてやるよ｡
Yeah, I'll redesign the thing so a grade schooler can drive it.
《俺は サラリーマン時代と
変わらぬ車開発で…》
I'm working on vehicle designs the same way I did at my old job,
《一方あいつは 新たな訓練のため
ロシアへ…か》
while he's going to Russia for new training...
《何回目だ｡こ～やって
あいつの背を見るの…》
How many times have I watched him leave me behind?
《まあいい｡
すぐに追いついてやる》
Whatever.
I'll catch up soon enough.
⦅ありがとな ムッちゃん⦆
Thanks, Mu.
⦅それから…⦆
One more thing...
⦅俺らは生きて
一緒に月面に立とうぜ！⦆
We're going to stand on the moon together, alive!
⦅バカヤロウ⦆
Fool.
⦅あ 当たり前だ⦆
That goes without saying.
《とりあえず
リハーサルは終了だな 日々人》
I guess that counted as a rehearsal, Hibito.
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
Hibito!
(フレディ)ヒビト…ヒビト…
ヒビト！
Hibito!
(バディ)おい 聞こえてんのか！
こっち見ろ ヒビト！
Hey, can you hear us?
Look at us, Hibito!
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
(フレディ)顔色悪いぞ｡
You don't look too good...
(フレディ)大丈夫か？
Are you okay?
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
いったん中止だ｡
I'm calling it off.
O-Okay...
カレン リンダ 聞こえたか
げんあつ
減圧は中止だ！
Karen! Linda! Do you read me?
Restore the pressure!
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
ああ…なんだろう ごめん｡
Yeah, sorry... Not sure what happened.
ヒビト 今日は休んでおけ｡
作業はリンダに代わってもらう｡
Hibito, get some rest.
Linda can take your place.
え!?平気だよ ちょっと休めば｡
Huh?
I'll be fine after a little rest.
No, it's a bad idea.
(フレディ)いや やめておけ｡
しんでんず
しんぱくすう
かこきゅう
心拍数の増加と過呼吸➡
High pulse, hyperventilation,
体温上昇 それに
吐き気も訴えてます｡➡
hyperthermia, and nausea, as well.
ただし 今のところ➡
However, these symptoms only appear under certain conditions.
症状は 決まった状況下でのみ
あらわれるようです｡
決まった状況とは？
What are the conditions?
They occur when he puts on a spacesuit.
船外服を着る時です｡
一種のパニック障害と思われます｡
I believe he's suffering from a panic disorder.
きかん
帰還するまで
ヒビトの船外活動は禁止させろ｡➡
Do not allow Hibito to participate in any EVA before he returns.
よあつふく
与圧服は着れるのか？
Can he wear pressure suits?
(サイモン)ええ…今のところ｡
Yes, as of now,
なによりも
無事に帰還するのが先決だ｡
there haven't been any issues.
(管制官)ヒビトの心拍数が
上昇してますが…｡
Hibito's pulse is rising.
本人に伝える必要はない！
予定通り打ち上げてやろう｡
He doesn't need that information.
Continue with the launch.
大丈夫？ヒビト｡
苦しいのか？
Are you okay, Hibito?
Are you in any pain?
なに 言ってんの 大丈夫 大丈夫｡
What's this about?
I'm doing just fine.
さあ…帰ろう！
Okay, let's go home.
たいきけん
(管制官)大気圏 突入開始！
Commence reentry sequence!
Since Hibito's return, we've run tests,
帰還後のヒビトの検査結果ですが
やはり 同じ症状が｡➡
and he's showing the same symptoms.
ただ 船外服を着た時に
いつでも発作が起こる➡
However, it appears the attacks aren't triggered by the spacesuit itself.
というわけではありません｡
船外服を着ながら➡
But when he wears one in a zero-gravity environment such as the pool,
無重力環境訓練のプｰルに入るなど
危険性を伴う状況での緊張が➡
the sense of danger causes stress
例の恐怖体験を思い出させ
そして発作に…｡
that reminds him of his terrible ordeal,
which then triggers the attack.
現在
Does that mean Hibito can no longer participate in EVA?
それはつまり ヒビトはもう
船外活動ができないと…｡
残念だがヒビト…
船外活動ができないうちは➡
I'm sorry to have to tell you this, Hibito.
But we can't send you on lunar missions if you can't participate in EVA.
君を月のミッションには
加えられない｡
It's been so long since I looked up at the moon
Though it's always keeping a cold eye on me
Yeah, it always keeps a cold eye on me
I wanna rough up this rotten way home
But even if it makes me mad
I can't take my eyes off it. Yeah, I can't take my eyes off it
I can't take my eyes off that dazzling smile
What did I want back then?
What was I looking for?
I should've known my tears would take me to my dreams
Blow this gloomy reality away for me
I want to see how tiny our huge worries seem
From up in that dark ocean of space
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#72 Hibito's Disorder
A panic disorder.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)＜パニック障害？＞
＜このことは ムッちゃんには…＞
Don't tell Mu about this.
＜大丈夫 わかってる｡
何があっても ムッタの前には➡
Don't worry, I understand.
No matter what happens, you want to act like nothing is wrong around Mutta.
何事もなかったみたいに
戻りたいのよね＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Hibito's Disorder"
Mr. Hibbit!
イェーイ！
やぁ みんな 僕 ヒビット！
Yay!
Hey, everyone! I'm Hibbit!
月へ行くためには
色んな訓練が必要なんだって！
It looks like I need lots of training to go to the moon.
ニンジン食べる？
Want some carrots?
Houston Ellington Airport
フン！フン！フーン！
訓練といえば 筋トレ！
これしかねえ！
To me, training means lifting weights.
That's the only way to train...
じょうわんにとうきん
見よ この上腕二頭筋！
こうはいきん
だいきょう
後背筋！そして大胸…｡
Look at these biceps, these lats,
and these pecs—
そんなんじゃ 月どころか
となり町にも行けね～ぜ！お？
That won't get you out of the city, let alone to the moon.
Oh?
このブタだれ？
さあ？
Who's this hog?
Dunno.
誰がブタだ！
ワシは飛行訓練の教官➡
I'm no hog!
I'm the flight instructor, Deneil Pig.
デニールピッグだ！
要するにブタだよね｡
ウィ！ウィ！
That means he's a hog, right?
どうだ 飛行訓練は！お？
How do you like flight training?
イエーイ!!
ちょっと せまいけど最高！
Yay! It's cramped in here, but it's great!
ウィ！ウィ！
ちなみに知ってるか｡ブタってのは
意外と体脂肪率が低い｡
And did you know...
Hogs have a relatively low percentage of body fat.
頭のノートにメモっとけ！お？
Put that in the notebook in your head.
オッケー！
Okay!
Hog
ウハハハ…！そういうことじゃ
ないんだけどな！
That wasn't what I meant.
ま～た らいしゅ～！
See you next week!